<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The danger of desertion or, A farvvell sermon of Mr. Thomas Hooker, sometimes minister of Gods Word at Chainsford in Essex; but now of New England. Preached immediately before his departure out of England. Together with ten particular rules to be practised every day by converted Christians.</title>
            <author>Hooker, Thomas, 1586-1647.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86525</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2645</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E171_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1512</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859801</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859801</idno>
            <idno type="VID">111900</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86525)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 111900)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 30:E171[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The danger of desertion or, A farvvell sermon of Mr. Thomas Hooker, sometimes minister of Gods Word at Chainsford in Essex; but now of New England. Preached immediately before his departure out of England. Together with ten particular rules to be practised every day by converted Christians.</title>
                  <author>Hooker, Thomas, 1586-1647.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 29, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G. M. for George Edwards in the Old Baily in Greene-Arbour, at the signe of the Angell,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"The rule of the new creature" has separate caption title; pagination and register are continuous.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Jeremiah XIV, 9 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Farewell sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian converts --  Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:111900:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE DANGER OF DESERTION: <hi>OR</hi> A FARVVELL SERMON of Mr. <hi>Thomas Hooker,</hi> Somtimes Miniſter of Gods Word at <hi>Chainſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> in <hi>Eſſex;</hi> but now of <hi>New</hi> ENGLAND. Preached immediately before his departure <hi>out of old</hi> ENGLAND.</p>
            <p>TOGETHER, WITH TEN PARTICVLAR rules to be practiſed every day by converted <hi>Christians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>G.M.</hi> for <hi>George Edwards</hi> in the Old Baily in Greene-Arbour, at the Signe of the <hi>Angell.</hi> 1641.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:111900:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:111900:2"/>
            <head>The Epiſtle to the READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>CHRISTIAN READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Author of this Sermon, while be li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved here among us, gave God proofe of his ſolid judgement, acute wit, strong memory, honeſt heart, pious diſpoſition, and utter detestation, as of prophaneſse, ſo of ſuperſtition. He was trained up in <hi>Immanuel Colledge Cambridge,</hi> where he ſhewed his indefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigable induſtry about his owne ſtudies, and conſciona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble fidelity about his pupils and their studies. His opinion about the Doctrine maintained in the Church of England, ſince the reformation thereof, was <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox;</hi> but his conſcience about the Diſcipline and Ceremonies thereof was ſcrupulous; yet ſo, as he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ſuch as he obſerved ſincere and entire in the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, though he differed from them in circumstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Nor he, nor many of his brethren like him, that were forced to leave old England to enjoy the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of their tender conſciences, deſerted their places in any envy, hatred, or other like diſreſpect againſt the Church of England (like many rigid Separatiſts,
<pb facs="tcp:111900:3"/>who account her ſelfe to be no Church, and her Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters to be no Miniſters,) but partly to enjoy a greater liberty to themſelves then here they could, partly to propogate the Goſpell, and make it knowne to ſuch as had not heard of it before. Take inſtance of this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors diſpoſition, by this his Farwell Sermon. Reade it, and obſerve it well, and thou ſhalt finde therein ſavoury of piety mixed with ſincerity, and of zeale with meekneſſe. Reade it I ſay, and then cenſure it, it needs no other to commend it then it ſelfe, neither can any other doe it better then it ſelfe.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:111900:3"/>
            <head>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. HOOKERS FARVVELL SERMON, At his departure out of ENGLAND.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>JEREMIAH 14.9. at the latter end.</bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We are called by thy Name, leave us not.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Wo things are intended and expreſſed by the Holy ghoſt, from the 1. verſe, to the thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth.</p>
            <p>Firſt, a denuntiation of judgement, and that reacheth to the 17. verſe, and that is <hi>ſword and famine.</hi> Firſt, he
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:111900:4"/>would ſend the famine, and then the ſword, and would not be intreated.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in the 8. verſe, we have the importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate prayer of the Church, to turne away theſe judgements; and the prayer is marvellous ſweet, partly in confeſſion, <hi>where they confeſse their ſinnes, and ſeeke to God for ſuccour againſt them:</hi> As if they ſhould ſay, Loe we are as baſe as baſe can be, and therefore help for the Lords ſake, and thus they make their ſupplication in the 7. and 8. verſes, and this ſhort prayer diſcovers it ſelfe, partly in the things prayed for, and partly in the manner, and the holy Prophet intending this is very ſweet in it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, they pray that God will not take away his preſence from them, <hi>Why stayeſt thou but a night?</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, it is marvellous ſtrange, that thou behaveſt thy ſelfe as a ſtranger.</p>
            <p>Thou ſeeſt our ſorrowes, and helpeſt not. Thou ſeeſt our trouble, and ſuccoureſt not. Thou ſtandeſt, and ſeeſt Jeruſalem in trouble, and Iuda in miſery, but thou helpeſt not. It is ſtrange that thou the great God of Hoſts ſtandeſt as a man aſtoniſhed: thou haſt received us, but now thou ſtandeſt as a man amazed, as if thou waſt weary of thy worke, and couldeſt doe no more: As if he ſhould ſay, Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem cannot be ſuccoured, &amp; Iudaea cannot be ſaved.</p>
            <p>Secondly, they beg that God would not take away his preſence from them, <hi>Leave us not to our ſelves.</hi> Let us ſee thy face, if that we dye in thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, though thou helpeſt not, yet it dothus good to looke on a Saviour, they are acquainted firſt that thou art the hope of Iſrael. Alas! if thou forſake,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:111900:4"/>us, our hope is loſt, our hope is not in the means, our hope is in thee, <hi>leave us not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, thou art the Saviour of Iſrael, and it is that that thou takeſt upon thee, and thou haſt made thy ſelfe a Saviour, and now is the time of trouble, performe what thou haſt undertaken.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, thou art in the midſt of us, thou art a great comforter, ready to ſuccour us. What wilt thou ſee us periſh when thou art ſo near us? 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 4.6. <hi>Even as the Arke in the midſt of the campe:</hi> as if he ſhould ſay, he lives in the midſt of us, and will not ſave us.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>we are called by thy Name,</hi> we have inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in thee, to whom ſhould ſervants go for ſafety, but to their Maſter? to whom ſhould the wife goe, but to her husband? we have intereſt in thee, <hi>leave us not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now we will meddle only with the latter clauſe, <hi>leave us not.</hi> God might leave them, but they beg that he would not, that is their Amento the Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, though thou ſtandeſt by, and wilt not help, yet let us not dye in thy preſence. This is the great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of the Saints, they deſire not to be left of God, though God may juſtly leave them,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That God may justly leave off a people,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Doct.</note>
               <hi>and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>church a Nation.</hi> Iſrael ſuſpected it, and feared it: It is that that they prayed againſt, that God would not leave them. I doe not ſay that God will caſt off his elect eternally; but thoſe that are onely in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward covenant, with him he may, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Heare O ye heavens, I have nurſed up children,</hi> that is, the Iewes, there is an outward vocation, and for ſuch God may
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:111900:5"/>caſt them off. Brethren, caſt your thoughts afar off. What is become of thoſe famous Churches, <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gamus</hi> and <hi>Thyatira,</hi> and the reſt? Who would have thought that <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> ſhould have bin made a heap of ſtones, and a vagabond people? <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 7.9. <hi>Plead with your mother, and call her Loammi, ye are not my people, and I will not be your God.</hi> Thus as I may ſay, he ſues out a bill of divorcement, as it was in the old Law, thoſe that had any thing againſt their wives, ſued our a bill of divorcement, and ſo doth God, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.2. <hi>ſhe is not my people, nor my beloved, let her caſt away her fornications and idolatry, leſt I make her as at the firſt,</hi> that is, in Egypt poore and miſerable: as if he ſhould ſay to England, plead with England my Miniſters, in the way of my truth, and ſay unto them, let them caſt away their rebellions, leſt I make her as I found her in captivity in the dayes of bondage.</p>
            <p>But how doth God depart from a people?<note place="margin">Ob.</note>
            </p>
            <p>When he takes away his love from a people,<note place="margin">Anſ.</note> and as his reſpect, ſo his means too.</p>
            <p n="2">2. When he takes away his protection by taking downe the wals, that is, theſe two great meanes of ſafety, Magiſtrates and Miniſters.</p>
            <p n="3">3. When inſtead of counſelling, comes in bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing, and in ſtead of teaching, dawbing, when God either takes away the hedges, or the ſtakes are rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, then God is going.</p>
            <p n="4">4. When God takes away the benefit of both theſe helps, and they are ſignes of Gods depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</p>
            <p>May God caſt off a people,<note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</note> and unchurch ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:111900:5"/>then let it teach us to caſt off all ſecurity, for miſeries are nigh by all probabilities. When we obſerve what God hath done for us, all things are ripe for ruine, and yet we feare it not, we promiſe ſafety to our ſelves, and conſider not that England is like to be harrowed, wee cannot entertaine a thought that England ſhall be deſtroyed; when there are ſo many profeſſors in it, we cannot be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded of it, according to the conviction of our judgements, either it muſt not be, or not yet, as if it were impoſſible for God to leave England, as if God were a cockering father over lewd and ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne children: God may leave a Nation that is but in outward covenant with him, and why not En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland?</p>
            <p>Englands ſinnes have been great, yea and their mercies great. England hath been a mirror of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, yet God may leave us, and make us a mirrour of his juſtice. Looke how he ſpake to the people in <hi>Ier.</hi> 7. <hi>that bragged of the Temple of the Lord, Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices and offerings:</hi> And what may not God which deſtroyed Shilo, deſtroy thee O England? Goe to Bohemia, from thence to the Palatinate, and ſo to Denmarke. Imagine you were there, what ſhall you ſee, nothing elſe but as Travellers ſay, Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches made heaps of ſtones, and thoſe Bethels wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Gods name was called upon, are made defiled Temples for Satan and ſuperſtition to raigne in? You cannot goe two or three ſteps, but you ſhall ſee the heads of dead men, goe a little further, and you ſhall ſee their hearts picked out by the fowles of the ayre, whereupon you are ready to conclude
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:111900:6"/>that Tilly hath been there: Thoſe Churches are become deſolate, and why not England? Goe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Cities and Townes, and there you ſhall ſee many compaſſed about with the chaines of capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, and every man bemoaning himſelfe. Doe but caſt your eyes abroad, and there you ſhall ſee poore fatherleſſe children ſending forth their breaches, with feare, crying to their poore helpleſſe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Step but a little farther, and you ſhall ſee the ſad wife bemoaning her husband, and that is her miſery, that ſhe cannot dye ſoone enough; and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſhe makes funerall Sermons of her children within her ſelfe, for that the Spaniard may get her little ones, and bring them up in Popery and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition; and then ſhe weeps and conſiders with her ſelfe: If my husband be dead, it is well, happily he is upon the racke, or put to ſome cruell tortures, and then ſhe makes funerall Sermons, and dyes a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred times before ſhe can dye. Caſt your eyes afar off, ſet your ſoules in their ſoules ſtead, and imagine it were your owne condition, why may not England be thus, who knowes but it may be my wife, when he heares of ſome in torments? Ah! Brethren, be not high minded, but feare, as we have this bounty on the one ſide, ſo may we have this ſeverity on the other; therefore prancke not up your ſelves with fooliſh imaginations, as who dare come to En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, the Spaniards have enough, the French are too weake: Be not deceived, who thought Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem the Lady of Kingdomes, whither the Tribes went to worſhip, ſhould become a heap of ſtones, a vagabond people, and why not England? Learne
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:111900:6"/>therefore to heare and feare, God can be a God without England, doe not ſay there are many Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in it, can God be beholding to you for your Religion? No ſurely, for rather then he will main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſuch as profeſſe his Name and hate him, <hi>he will raiſe up of theſe ſtones children unto Abraham;</hi> He will rather goe to the Turks, and ſay you are my people, and I will be your God. But will you let God goe, England? Why are you ſo content to let him goe? Oh! lay hold on him, yea hang on him, and ſay thou ſhalt not goe. Doe you thinke that Rome will part with her religion, and forſake her gods? nay, an hundred would rather loſe their lives. Will you let God goe? Oh England plead with your God! and let him not depart. You ſhould onely part with your rebellions, he will not part with you. <hi>Leave us not.</hi> We ſee the Church is very importunate to keep God with them ſtill, they lay hold on God with words of argument.</p>
            <p>Thou hope of Iſrael, doe not leave us: they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet God with their prayers, and watch him at the Townes end that he might not goe away. No thou ſhalt not goe away, thou ſhalt abide with us ſtill, they are importunate with God not to leave them.</p>
            <p>Hence note this Doctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That it is the importunate deſire of Saints to keep God with them.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Doct.</note> This people you ſee cared not ſo much for the famine and ſword, ſo God leaves them not: Good Lord leave us not, this was their prayer, and we cannot blame them, all things being conſidered; for it was their griefe that God ſtood by, and would not help, why ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:111900:7"/>thou as a man aſtoniſhed? but good Lord leave us not, they cannot abide to heare of that, much leſſe to beare it; thus they did, and thus the Saints of God ſhould doe. For the proofe, ſee <hi>Exod.</hi> 33.15. there <hi>Moſes</hi> might have gone up upon faire termes, <hi>thou ſhalt poſſeſſe the land, and peace and proſperity ſhall be with thee;</hi> but what ſayes <hi>Moſes? If I might have Canaan, and all the delights, yet carry us not hence, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept thy preſence be with us, Pſal.</hi> 80.7, 19. this is the ſtay and ſtring that he ſticks on. <hi>Turne us againe O Lord God of Hoſts, and cauſe thy face to ſhine upon us:</hi> as if he ſhould ſay, here is proſperity.</p>
            <p>But what is the preſence of God?<note place="margin">Ob.</note>
            </p>
            <p>In one word,<note place="margin">Anſ.</note> it is the particular favour of God expreſſed in his ordinances, and all the good and ſweet that followeth there. The purity of Gods word and worſhip, is that which God reveales himſelfe in. It is not gold, wealth, and proſperity, that makes God to be our God. There is more gold in the Weſt-Indians, then in all Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome beſides; but in is Gods ordinances in the vertue of them that, brings Gods preſence. God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſook Shilo where he dwelt, becauſe his ordinances were not there, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.5. <hi>when the Arke left them, God left them:</hi> When Gods ordinances were there in the purity of them, then God was there; for he is principally there where his ordinances are in the purity of them. Hence it was that <hi>Cain</hi> was caſt out of Gods preſence, becauſe he was caſt out of the Church where his ordinances were, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.14. If that a people doe outwardly worſhip God, and ſincerely mend things that be amiſſe, they may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:111900:7"/>If Sodome and Gomorrah had but legally repented, they had remained to this day. Hence it is that the Saints of God are ſo urgent for Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, and in that moſt men ſo ſleight them. While it is thus with us is not England ripe? is not ſhe wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God? nay, ſhe is fed fat for the ſlaughter. It was not ſo with the Saints and people of God in former times, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.4. It was <hi>Davids</hi> great and grand deſire, <hi>that he might dwell in the houſe of the Lord, Pſal.</hi> 42.4. <hi>his ſoule panted after Gods ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</hi> The point teacheth us thus much, That the Saints are wondrous importunate to keep God in his ordinances.</p>
            <p>But what if a man want preaching,<note place="margin">Ob.</note> may not he want it, and yet goe to Heaven?</p>
            <p>The arguments are cleare,<note place="margin">Anſ.</note> the Saints maintaine God in his ordinances, the want of which is under the penalty of death and condemnation. Gold can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not feed a hungry man, but bread he would have, becauſe that he hath need of: ſo the Saints of God are marvellous importunate to keep God in his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, ſo that though they weare a ragged coat, or be pinched with hunger; yet he wants God more then theſe, either food or rayment. <hi>David</hi> in the 37. Pſalme, <hi>fretteth at the proſperity of the wicked;</hi> but at the laſt breaks off, and marke what a conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion he makes, and comes to, <hi>whom have I in heaven but thee?</hi> as if he ſhould have ſaid, Let them have what they will, I have nothing but thee. Why ſo? <hi>Thou art the ſtrength of my heart, and my portion for ever:</hi> Thou art the ſtrength of the heart, Shewing that all things in the world cannot help the heart
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:111900:8"/>without God. A man were as good offer yron to a hungry man to refreſh him, or ayre to feed him, as to ſay, riches, eaſe, and honour will help thy diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſoule: Theſe will never eſtabliſh a man, he may hope to have comfort in them; but his ſoule ſhall be gravelled and troubled. It muſt be the God of peace that muſt ſpeak peace to a troubled ſoul: It muſt be the God of ſalvation that can comfort a damned ſoule; that kindneſſe will comfort, that is the ſtrength of the heart, and portion for ever, and then no marvell the ſoule call for God: The ſoule cares not, though happily the purſe be filled, for it cryes and ſighs, I am damned. Happily the pallate may be pleaſed; but the poore ſoule cryes, I may goe to hell, and to the Devill. Now God comes, and he ſupplyes all, for where he comes, there is every good gift: If once a man hath God, he hath all good things with him. God bleſſed <hi>Obadiahs</hi> houſe for the Arkes ſake. Now the Arke was a type of Chriſt, where he comes all good things follow: When God comes, <hi>we are married unto him, Hoſ,</hi> 2.19. As when a wife is married, her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band is hers: ſo God &amp; all is thine, &amp; what wouldſt thou have more? He ſpeaks to the raine, and it heares the corne and wine, and that heares Iſraell. Hell and Death are thy ſervants; but now you that have outward things, profits, and proſperity, &amp;c. you have them with a curſe, unleſſe you have God with them: Get God therefore, if he forſakes a man, all miſeries befall him, and then woe beto him, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 9.13. Ah! it is true indeed, woe beto that heart which God is departed from. When God
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:111900:8"/>who is the God of mercy is gone away from him, who wil pitty that ſoul that will not ſubmit to Gods peace, conſolation, and ſalvation. When God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parteth, all miſeries follow on amaine: when the banks are broken downe, the Sea breaks forth: ſo when God departs, all miſeries come; for that man that makes no conſcience of outfacing God in his Ordinances, marke what the Text ſaith, <hi>Deut.</hi> 31. 37. <hi>I will forſake them, and many miſeries ſhall befall them.</hi> If God be gone, the Floud-gates are drawne dry, and in comes all miſery. You will ſay, are not all theſe things againſt us, ſeeing God is not with us? If we would avoid woe and ſorrow, and killing and ſlaying one another. Would the women be glad to ſee their husbands killed before their tender eyes, the men to ſee the women taken out of the world by the hands of wicked men. If not then, leave not God, but hold him faſt, then all evill will depart, and ſo holding God he will keep us from miſery.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> To condemne 2 ſorts of people.<note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</note> If the Saints be marvellous importunate to have God with them, what ſhall we thinke of thoſe that are weary of the Almighty, who ſay to him depart from us: But you will ſay, ſuch are to be chronicled, we have none ſuch among us. Thou that art a ſervant, and rejecteſt thy Maſters command, thou rejecteſt God. Why ſhould a man ſay that they be ſo long and ſo long in prayer, and ſay, what man knowes not what he ſayes, he ſpeaks this becauſe that he is weary of the Ordinances, and would be freed from them, and God will doe it one day. Alas poore ſoule,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:111900:9"/>thou couldeſt pitty thy condition, thou art weary of Gods Ordinances, weary of Gods mercies, weary of his patience, &amp; preſence. Thou ſhalt one day be deprived of his preſence, and ſhut up with the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of God and goodneſſe in the blacke Tophet, where the worme never dyes, nor the fire never goes out, then thy crying will doe thee no good. God will be God in thy deſtruction, he will ſpurne thouſands, and ten thouſands ſuch as thou art downe to hell, where thou ſhalt be an everlaſting object of his never dying wrath, though thou coul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt ſcale the heavens with thy teares, and ſhrill voice: Though thou couldeſt be heard to cry out of the dungeon, yet thy help is never the nearer, thy God is gone. I admoniſh thee what to doe, lay thee downe and patiently endure his deſerved wrath; Nay, marke what I ſay, a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred hels thou haſt deſerved, and in thoſe hels to lye a hundred yeares, nay for ever. Hold thy ſelfe contented with thy condition, for <hi>thou haſt choſen death rather then life, Ier.</hi> 31.8. God ſhould wrong himſelfe and thee, if that he did not give thee thy chuſing. Will not theſe things move you my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren? that you may be ſo happily wiſe, as to chuſe life rather than death, Lord grant it, for he delights not in your deſtruction. One word more, to leave impreſſion in your hearts: I deſire your ſoules health, though my meat ſeeme bitter; yet it is the mind of God it ſhould be ſo, and therefore, thou man or woman, whoſoever thou art that canſt not abide preaching, but ſtandeſt on thornes, to have the Sermon done, that ſayeſt too much of one thing
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:111900:9"/>is good for nothing. Thou doeſt as good as ſay, what need have we of that, a little of that, and more of pleaſure, here is thy delight and deſire. Know this whoſoever thou art, that haſt ill-will to the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of God, thou wouldſt have no ſuch Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, thou ſhalt have thy deſire, when the Trumpet ſhall blow, thy eares ſhall tingle, with that ſentence, <hi>Depart from me.</hi> Thou that art weary of God, get thee downe to hell, I ſay, God will ſet his teeth at thee, and ſtamp thee downe to hell with thy baſe luſts: Then will God ſay, I have fed thee on earth this 20, 30, 40, 50, perhaps 60 yeares, and yet my milde words could not beare rule in thee, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile with thee, and now get thee to hell, and there remaine for ever. Thinke this with thy ſelfe, God will ſo ſerve thee <hi>proud Captaine, King, or Monarch, Iſa.</hi> 30.33. The Text ſaith, <hi>he will make bonfires upon their bones about their eares,</hi> thus he will get himſelfe glory by your deſtruction: But you will ſay to me being a King or Monarch, I doe not feare any ſuch puniſhment ſhall befall me; but God will ſay, be he a King that rules or raignes, yet as he hath rejected God, ſo God will reject him. He is a King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, and therefore ſuch a one as will laugh at thy deſtruction. Take notice of this, and ſay thus to your ſelves: Is he a good childe that cannot abide the preſence of his father: Is ſhe a good wife that cannot abide the preſence of her husband: So is he a good creature that cannot abide the preſence of his Creator.</p>
            <p>This rebukes Gods owne people.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</note> We ſee the Goſpell going, brethren, I wonder you heare no
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:111900:10"/>better ſtand up &amp; heare, and God give you grace to underſtand. I deale plainly with you, and tell you what God hath told me: I muſt tell you on pane of ſalvation, will you give eare and beleeve. I poore Embaſſador of God am ſent to doe this meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage unto you, though I am low, yet my meſſage is from above, he that ſent me, grant that it may be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved for his ſake. Suppoſe God hath told me this night that he will deſtroy England, and lay it waſte, what ſay you brethren to it? It is my meſſage that God bade me doe, he expects your anſwer, what ſayeſt thou oh England, I muſt returne an anſwer to my Maſter that ſent me to night, why ſpeake you not an anſwer? I muſt have one. Doe you like well of it, would you have England deſtroyed? would you put the old men to trouble, and the young men to the ſword? would you have your women wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, and your maids defiled? would you have your children, your deare ones to be throwne upon the pikes, and daſhed againſt the wals? or would you have them brought up in idolatry under the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of preaching, which is worſt of all? would you ſee thoſe Temples wherein we worſhip God burnt, and your owne houſes? will you ſee Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land laid waſte without inhabitants? are you wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to it? are you content? God bade me aske, why doe you not anſwer me? I muſt not ſtirre with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it, I muſt have it, I am an importunate Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, ſend me not away ſad, ſpeake comfortably and cheerfully unto me. Are you willing to have God with you ſtill, you are, are you not? I am glad of it; but you muſt not onely ſay ſo, but uſe the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:111900:10"/>meanes, plead with God: And though his hand be up, and his ſword drawne; yet ſuffer him not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy, but to ſheath it in the bloud of our enemies, God grant it, and I ſhould be glad to ſee England flouriſh ſtill, and ſo are you, are you not? you are. Now if it come to paſſe that England be not, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed and laid deſolate, thanke your ſelves, and not God, he delights not in it. We may take up the complaint of the Prophet, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 64.7. <hi>No man ſtirs up himſelfe to lay hold upon God:</hi> For this is our mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, if that we have quietneſſe and commodity we are well enough, thus we play mock-holy-day with God, the Goſpell we make it our pack-horſe: God is going, his glory is departing, England hath ſeene her beſt dayes, and now evill dayes are befal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling us: God is packing up his Goſpell, becauſe no body will buy his wares, nor come to his price. Oh lay hands on God! and let him not goe out of your coaſts, he is a going, ſtop him, and let not thy God depart, lay ſiege againſt him with humble and hearty cloſing with him, ſuffer him not to ſay, as if that he were going, farewell, or fare ill England, God hath ſaid he will doe this, and becauſe that he hath ſaid it, he will doe it, therefore prepare to meet thy God O England! <hi>Amos</hi> 4.12. leaſt God complaine of thee as he did of Ieruſalem, leſt my ſoule depart from thee, and I make thee a deſolate land not inhabited.</p>
            <p>Thus we ſee that the godly hath done, and this muſt be our care; but let it be our Copy, claſpe about the Lord Jeſus as <hi>Mary</hi> did, they have bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the Ice, let us goe after them, this is our attone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:111900:11"/>day, we have nothing to doe with to morrow, this is the day of reconciliation, we are at odds with God; and to end all controverſies, let us labour to prevaile with God, and never loſe his preſence, <hi>I ſought but I found him not, Cant.</hi> 3.2. <hi>and when I found him not, I followed and ſought him, till that I found him.</hi> Our God is going, and doe you ſit ſtill on your beds? would you have and keep the Goſpell with theſe lazie wiſhes? ariſe, ariſe, and downe on your knees, and intreat God to leave his Goſpell to your poſterity. Shall we diſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit our infants of ſuch a bleſſing? ſhall we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reave them of the Goſpell, which ſhould be the life of our lives, and ſo to have them brought up in ſuperſtition? No Lord, we cannot endure this, give us not health or wealth; but give us thy Goſpell Lord, that is our plea, &amp; when we have found God let us bring him home to our families, that as we have made him our God, ſo let him be the God of ours in time of affliction. We will cry, <hi>Lord have mercy upon us,</hi> then we ſhall be glad of him. Oh beloved! carry God home with you, lay hold on him, let him not goe, ſay he is our husband, let him not goe for your little ones, and ſo let us leave God to be a father unto thee.</p>
            <p>But how may we keep the Lord?<note place="margin">Ob.</note> it is worth the while, it is comfortable, <hi>for at his right hand are pleaſures for evermore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you will come to the price,<note place="margin">Anſ.</note> you ſhall have him. The meanes are theſe:</p>
            <p n="1">1. You muſt prepare roome for him, for he is a King, and a King ſends an harbinger before him to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:111900:11"/>prepare roome for him againſt he comes to any place: ſo muſt you doe by cleanſing your ſelves from every evill courſe; therefore <hi>come out of her,</hi> ſarth the Lord to his people, <hi>touch no uncleane thing, and then I will be your God, and you ſhall be my people, Rev.</hi> 18.19. So brethren come out of all evill ſinfull pleaſures and practiſes, and then you may expect Gods comming into your houſes; when you ſit by the fire, and when you lye upon your beds, thinke thus with your ſelves: What an equall condition doth he propound? doth he require no more but to part with a ſinne, a luſt, a Dalila, which thou mayeſt ſpare as well as water out of thy ſhooes, or out of thy boſome; yea it is ſo. Will God keep company in the paths of ſinne? what is this his proffer? what are the tearmes no harder? what then ſhould I doe but bid ſinne adieu? would you have God to be your God, and will you not keep out of ſinne? If not, he will not be your God: But now let every ſoule forſake his uncleanneſſe, and God will come to that ſoule; and therefore that place is marvellous ſweet, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.8. <hi>You ſhall call and God ſhall ſay, here I am, if that you will forſake your evill courſes.</hi> Thus you ſee you have as faire an offer, as faire a warning as God can propound.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As you muſt prepare roome for God, ſo you muſt give him content, let him have his will. Where the King comes, there he will have all ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his minde: ſo it is with God, if he may have his owne worſhip you pleaſe him well, you muſt dreſſe his diſh according to his tooth; but when you put poiſon into his meat, you diſcontent
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:111900:12"/>him, then you doe not give him his mind, you muſt lay aſide all ſuperſtition and errours; then you pleaſe his tooth above all, when your ſoules ſubmit to his truth: <hi>At the name of Ieſus every knee ſhall bow.</hi> This is not meant of the word <hi>Ieſus,</hi> to give a bow with the knee, and a ſtab at the heart: If ſo, why do we not bow at the word <hi>Iehovah,</hi> as at the word <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus;</hi> but the bowing at the word, the ſyllable is Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry: And here we doe not give him his minde; but the meaning of it is, that we ſhould worſhip him in ſpirit and truth.</p>
            <p n="3">3. As we give him his minde, ſo we muſt give him welcome alſo and entertainment: If you look lowring towards him, and grudge at him and his truth, no wonder but he goe away. This is the ſinne of <hi>England:</hi> We beare an ill will to God and his word, God hath done much for us of this land. <hi>What could he have done more for his vineyard, Iſa.</hi> 5. 4. <hi>but it brought forth fruit contrary to his expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> and therefore marke what he ſaith, <hi>I will take away the hedge thereof, it ſhall be troden downe:</hi> ſo will it be with us. Are we better then the old world? the ſame ſinnes that were found in them, are found in us: <hi>Sodome and Gomorrah on whom God rained fire and brimſtone,</hi> are not our ſinnes as great? and are there not as great ſinnes in us as were in <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> that was carried away captive? are we better then other Churches, then our brethren that have drunk ſo deeply of the cup of Gods wrath? what are we? I will tell you we are a burthen to God, he cannot beare us, he will thinke his paines well over when he hath deſtroyed us. You know all men are glad
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:111900:12"/>when their paines are over: ſo it is with God, we are a paine and a trouble to him, and why ſhould God goe continually in paine and trouble with us, who are worthy to be deſtroyed? If his decree once come forth, then ſhall <hi>England</hi> ſeeke peace, and ſhall not finde it. <hi>God will not pitty us,</hi> as in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 7.25. Ah! Brethren, what a heavy caſe is it, when a mercifull God doth ſhew himſelfe unmerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full? when a patient God will be impatient? O beloved! there is a hard time befalling us of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land; yet we conſider it not; lamentable is our time. God wept over Jeruſalem a long time: <hi>Oh that thou hadst known in this thy day the things that belong to thy peace, but now they are hid from thy eyes:</hi> So may I ſay to <hi>England,</hi> their Lord hath wept over it in mercy and patience a long time, but it hath not been taken notice of, God hath hid it from our eyes, what ſhall we doe when his mercy is turned into fury? and his patience into frowning? what ſhall we doe when we have leaſure to conſider what once we did enjoy? we can never prize Gods patience till that we finde the great want of it. Thus then the poore ſoule will ſay: There was a time when we might have been at peace with this patient God, but now it is hid from our eyes: I might have had mercy, but now the gate is ſhut, and not onely ſhut, but locked and barred too. Thus when people refuſe mercy, he ſends the contrary judgement, and then it will grieve and wound our ſoules to thinke what once we did enjoy; but that man that will bid God welcome to his heart, may goe ſinging to his grave.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:111900:13"/>
            <p n="4">4. You muſt be importunate with him to ſtay, and to continue, and count it a great favour that he will yet be intreated, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 37. <hi>Iacob wreſtled with God,</hi> and thus muſt we doe if we meane to keep him. You that live under the means, and will not walk in them, what great condemnation wil be to you, over to them that have not the meanes, as it is ſaid of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaum, Mat.</hi> 18. ſo ſay Ito <hi>England:</hi> Thou <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> which waſt lifted up to heaven with meanes ſhalt be abaſed and brought downe to hell; for if the mighty works which have been done in thee had been done in India or Turky, they would have repented ere this; therefore <hi>Capernaums</hi> place is <hi>Englands</hi> place, which is the moſt inſufferableſt tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all; and marke what I ſay, the poore native Turks and Infidels ſhall have a cooler ſummer par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour in hell then you; for we ſtand at a high rate, we were highly exalted, therefore ſhall our torments be the more to beare. The Lord write theſe things in our hearts with the finger of his owne Spirit for his Chriſts ſake, under whom we are all covered.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:111900:13"/>
            <head>THE RVLE OF THE NEW CREATVRE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>GAL. 6.16.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And as many as walke according to this rule, peace be on them, and mercy, and upon the Iſrael of God.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He rule of the new Creature, which is to be practiſed every day, by all beleevers, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of theſe ten particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars.</p>
            <p>Firſt be ſenſible of thy ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall ſin &amp; corruption, daily know how it enticeth thee to all evil, &amp; indiſpoſeth thee to all good; groan under it, and bewayle it as <hi>Paul</hi> did, 7. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. <hi>O wretched man that I-am, who ſhall deliver me from this body of death.</hi> Alſo take notice eſpecially of thy actuall ſinnes, or daily infirmities, in thought, word, and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:111900:14"/>deed, endeavour to make thy peace with thy God for them before thou goeſt to thy bed, by repenting and confeſſing of them to thy God; worke thy heart to grieve for them by ſome melting conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of Gods mercies towards thee, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.9. by beleeving or caſting thy ſelfe wholly on Chriſts righteouſneſſe, for removall of thy ſinne, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation with thy God, 3 <hi>Rom.</hi> 22, 23, 24, 25. <hi>Cleave to Gods promiſes of pardon and peace, Iſa.</hi> 43.25. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1. <hi>waiting till the Lord ſhall ſpeake peace to thy ſoule, Pſal.</hi> 85.6.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond rule of the new Creature is, get thy union with Chriſt, and intereſt in Chriſt cleare and confirmed unto thee daily more and more, <hi>that thou art a branchin that vine, a member in that body,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.3. this may be done three wayes.</p>
            <p>Firſt, by daily renewing thy faith in Chriſt, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially that act of faith, by which thy ſoule knits or tyes it ſelfe on Chriſt for ſalvation, cauſe thy ſoule every day in ſolemne manner to act that part, put forth this primitive act of faith in the whole part of thy ſoule. The daily exerciſe of this will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe and ſtrengthen the divine habit of faith in the ſoule, and make the ſoule ſenſible of every act of it: By frequent beleeving thou ſhalt feele at thy very heart root that thou doeſt beleeve: ſo ſhalt thou have witneſſe in thy ſelf, <hi>that thou art in Chriſt,</hi> 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.16.</p>
            <p>Secondly, by examining thy heart on what grounds thou takeſt Chriſt to be thine: as firſt, are thy grounds of taking Chriſt a ſight and ſenſe of thy ſinnes, of the guilt, power, and puniſhment of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:111900:14"/>them, and of thy miſery by them, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.13. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, are thy grounds of taking Chriſt, the want of Chriſt ſeene and felt at thy very heart, to juſtifie, ſanctifie, redeeme, and ſave thee, elſe thou art utterly undone for ever, and loſt everlaſtingly, <hi>Luk.</hi> 9.10. Thirdly, is thy ground of taking Chriſt, Gods free mercy &amp; generall offer of him to any that will take him by faith, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.16. Manifold promiſes to this purpoſe; the ground of all theſe offers — donations of Chriſt being <hi>free grace, rich mercy, undeſerved love, Eph.</hi> 2.4, 7. <hi>Titus</hi> 3.4, 5, 6, 7. Fifthly, is thy ground of taking Chriſt his ſweet and gracious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitation of <hi>ſuch to come to him, as are weary and heavy laden, Mat.</hi> 11.28. <hi>Buy of him as have no money, Iſa.</hi> 55.1. No worthineſſe at all, or deſert in our ſelves.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, are thy grounds of taking Chriſt thus, that as ſinfull wretches as thou art have been ſought of Chriſt, and found of him, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.10. Then why may not you; the more cleare thou deſireſt Chriſt, the more cleare will be thy title to him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In what manner thou deſireſt Chriſt to be thine.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Whether thou doeſt renounce wholly all opinion and conceit of thy owne righteouſneſſe and deſert, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.7, 8, 9, 10. So that thou commeſt to Chriſt empty of thy ſelfe, very vile, yea nothing in thy owne eyes, unworthy to receive him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whether thou layeſt hold on Chriſt alone with the empty hand of faith, joyning nothing at all with Chriſt in matters of ſalvation.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Whether thou finde God the Father drawing
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:111900:15"/>thy heart after him, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6.44. <hi>By hungring and pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting deſires, which will never be ſatisfied without him, ſo that the ſtreames both of thy judgement,</hi> 3 <hi>Phil.</hi> 18. alſo <hi>of thy affections,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.2. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.14.</p>
            <p n="4">4. If thou takeſt as a Lord to rule thee, as well <hi>as a Ieſus to ſave thee, Col.</hi> 2.6. one which is all to thee, thy wiſedome, thy righteouſneſſe, thy ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, thy redemption, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.3. <hi>thy ſpeciall food, Ioh.</hi> 5.6. <hi>thy rayment, Rom.</hi> 13.14. <hi>thy ſtrength, Phil.</hi> 4.13. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Whether thou ſeeke and wait for Chriſt out of the ſenſe of thy ſpirituall want and penury, in every ordinance publicke and private, Word, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, Prayer, Meditation, Conference, not as ones own works of ſanctification; but as they are Gods Ordinances, appointed of very purpoſe for the manifeſtation and communication of Chriſt to the ſoule.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third part of the rule of the new Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Labour to draw and derive from Chriſt by the pulling attractive force of faith, ſpeciall ability ſufficient for the day: Firſt, to performe all duties: ſecondly, to exerciſe all grace in the day: thirdly, to reſiſt and overcome all temptations and corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which ſhall befall thee in the day, make thy proviſion of grace and ſtrength from Chriſt, every morning fetch ſo much as you ſhall have occaſion to uſe all the day long; yea, and in all occaſions that ſhall fall out on the day; Goe to Chriſt ſtill for the wiſedome that muſt direct thee; for the holineſſe which muſt carry thee, and characteriſe thee; for the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:111900:15"/>ſhoulder that muſt beare thee: If they be croſſes, for the ſtrength that muſt ſuſtaine them: If they be temptations, performe them: If they be duties, act thy faith daily on the promiſes of grace and ſtrength, as <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.16. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.27. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 44.3. <hi>Zach.</hi> 10.12. Theſe are ſecurities given thee from God, that thou ſhal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> receive grace through the Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, which are the conduit-pipes, or inſtruments of conveying the ſame into the ſoule from Chriſt: This is to doe all in the ſtrength of Chriſt, and to take forth a great deale of Chriſt into the ſoule eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day, <hi>that not thou, but Chriſt may be in thee, Gal.</hi> 2.20.</p>
            <p>The fourth part of the new Creature, performe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> daily duties both in family, and in cloſet, eſpecially prayer, meditation, conference, reading with inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of affection, with diligence and delight, <hi>Ier.</hi> 48.10. <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.4. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 21.24. <hi>To this end watch to theſe duties, keep thy heart in a good frame for them, Eph.</hi> 6.18. <hi>undefiled with ſinne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, untainted with the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Take fit time for the performance of all, when tho art dull and ſluggiſh, begin the day with the thoughts of God.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Be ſubſtantiall with God in all theſe duties, endeavour to feele every duty at the very heart, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larging and inflaming thy affections. Theſe be du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of very great conſequence, which bring the greateſt comfort to thy ſoule, becauſe they aime at they ſoules good.</p>
            <p>The fifth rule of the new Creature.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, fortifie thy ſelfe very morning againſt
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:111900:16"/>thoſe ſpeciall inſts, to which by nature thou art moſt prone and often tempted, as pride, paſſion, inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate affections, covetouſneſſe, by argumenting and reaſoning within thy ſelfe, drawne from the ſad ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of it, as diſprofit, diſcomfort, diſgrace, &amp;c. La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to ſee the unreaſonableneſſe of thy ſinnes diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered unto thee, and make thy ſoule aſhamed of them; for examine and ponder with thy ſelfe, ſhall I be proud? then I am ſure to have a fall, for pride goes before a fall, and God accounts me as his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, for he reſiſts the proud. Shall I be angry? If I let paſſion in, I ſhall not keep Satan our, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.26. <hi>I ſhall grieve the holy Spirit of God, Eph.</hi> 4.30. Shall I be covetous? I cannot but be very ſinfull, for <hi>the love of money is the root of all evill,</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.10.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By pondring in thy mind the precepts in Gods book, threatnings againſt thy ſinnes, and judgments of God upon others; as on <hi>Herod</hi> for pride, <hi>Dives</hi> for voluptuouſneſſe <hi>Nabal</hi> for churliſhneſſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. By applying promiſes of mortification to thy heart, as a plaiſter to thy ſoule for ſubduing of thy corruptions daily, as <hi>Micah</hi> 9.10. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.14.</p>
            <p n="4">4. By drawing vertue from Chriſts death to thy ſoule, which hath in it a killing force of ſin, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.10. <hi>Num.</hi> 6.5.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> The ſixth part of the rule of the new Creature. Let thy heart be ſtrongly fixed on God by truſting on him, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 112.7. <hi>ſubmitting thy ſelfe to him,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.26. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.8. againſt thy feares, cares, tryals, troubles, afflictions of every day; <hi>for ſufficient to the day is the evill thereof, Mat.</hi> 6.31. to the end.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:111900:16"/>
            <p n="1">1. To foreſee prudently thy perſonall trials and troubles, whatſoever they are like to be, <hi>Prov.</hi> 22.3.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Goe hide and lay upthy ſelfe in God, run un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his name; for God is a rocke of ſalvation, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto a poore ſoule may continually reſort, God will give command to ſave us, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 71.3.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Eſpecially commit that very thing to God, put it into his hands, whatſoever thou deſireſt to keep, or feareſt to loſe, 2 <hi>Tim</hi> 1.12. be it life, liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, name, or friends, maintenance, whatſoever you would have reſolved of a doubt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.5. or ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, if it be want, removed; if it be a croſſe, <hi>Pſal</hi> 50.15. together with all other things, <hi>caſt all thy cares, ſorrowes, troubles, feares, on the Lord wholly, Mat.</hi> 6.31. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.7. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55.22.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Renew thy faith on thoſe promiſes every day, which moſt concernethy preſent ſtate: As for the promiſes of ſupply, <hi>if thou beeſt in want,</hi> as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.3. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.11. <hi>of direction if in doubt; of deliverance if in trouble, of a ſanctified uſe of all, Deut.</hi> 8.16. <hi>I am.</hi> 5. 11. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.10.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Labour to ſee Gods hand in every thing, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.9. <hi>beleeve his love, Heb</hi> 11.6.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Reſignethy ſelfe to him, <hi>Mat</hi> 26.39.</p>
            <p>The ſeventh part of the rule of the new Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Get a ſavoury relliſh of thy Chriſtian priviled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges with which thou art inveſted, as thou art a new creatrue in Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Of thy dignity, being the Son of God, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Of thy liberty, being freed out of all thy ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies hands.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:111900:17"/>
            <p n="3">3. Of the victory that thou haſt in Chriſt <hi>to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the world,</hi> 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.4. <hi>thou haſt victory over the evil of temptation and perſecutions, Rom.</hi> 8.35, 37. by thy faith.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Thou haſt an hedge of providence about thee, <hi>a guard of Angels, Pſal.</hi> 91.11. <hi>an incloſure of mercies, Pſal.</hi> 32.10. <hi>Gods promiſes are yet of protection, Heb.</hi> 13.5, 6.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Of thy riches, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.14. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.6.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Of the joyes, which are precious for kinde, plentifull for meaſure, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.11. they are <hi>thy Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters Ioy.</hi> Meditate on theſe ſeriouſly every day, and oppoſe thy pleaſures, profits, honours, which thou haſt by Chriſt, againſt the profit, pleaſure, honors of the world.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> The eighth rule of the new Creature, <hi>ſanctifie God in thy heart daily,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.15. <hi>get into thy heart the feare of God, Iſa.</hi> 8.13. <hi>delight in God, Pſal.</hi> 37.34.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Have ſerious thoughts of God in his nature, it is this will nouriſh the divine nature in thee.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Labour to admire God in his works, <hi>to tast his love in them, Pſal.</hi> 34.8. take notice of <hi>Gods anger in his judgements, Pſal.</hi> 119.120. <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.16.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Pray for a heart of fleſh, and apply the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes for that very end.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> The ninth part of the rule of the new Creature. Get a publicke Spirit <hi>to minde the things of Chriſt, Phil.</hi> 2.20, 21.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Mourne for the ſins of the time, call thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts <hi>Icabods,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 4.21.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Remember the afflictions of <hi>Ioſeph, Pſal.</hi> 137.6, 7. Simpathiſe with them, pray to God for them.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:111900:17"/>
            <p n="3">3. Minde ſignes of the times, as the commoneſt ſignes, contempt of Gods Ordinances, departure of his glory from his ordinances.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Incorrigibleneſſe under former judgements, as errours in opinion, declining from the truth of God, theſe precede temporall judgements, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 6.10, 11.</p>
            <p>The tenth rule of directions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Get thy heart more and more weaned from <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> the Creature, the Creature is empty, its not able to ſatisfie thee fully, nor make thee happy.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It cannot ſave thee from judgements, from death.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Its of a periſhing nature.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The wicked of the world have the greateſt part of theſe earthly bleſſings.</p>
            <p>Theſe ten rules are to be practiſed by Chriſtians every day.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
